<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The churches patience and faith in afflictions. Delivered in a sermon at the funerall of the right worshipfull, and vertuous Cecilia Lady Peyton, October, 30. In the parish church of Southfleet in Kent. By George Eves, rector of Hartley, neare adjoyning thereunto.</title>
            <author>Eves, George, 1613 or 14-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84178</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867054</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119344</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240922122</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1057_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208050</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867054</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867054e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84178)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119344)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 156:E1057[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The churches patience and faith in afflictions. Delivered in a sermon at the funerall of the right worshipfull, and vertuous Cecilia Lady Peyton, October, 30. In the parish church of Southfleet in Kent. By George Eves, rector of Hartley, neare adjoyning thereunto.</title>
                  <author>Eves, George, 1613 or 14-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for G. Bedell, and T. Collins, at the Middle-Temple Gate in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 31"; the second 1 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Peyton, Cecilia, --  Lady, d. 1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119344:1"/>
            <p>THE Churches Patience AND <hi>FAITH</hi> in <hi>AFFLICTIONS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Delivered in a Sermon at the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Right Worshipfull, and Vertuous <hi>CECILIA</hi> Lady <hi>PEYTON,</hi> October, 30.</p>
            <p>In the Parish Church of <hi>Southfleet</hi> in KENT.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Eves,</hi> Rector of <hi>Hartley,</hi> neare adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereunto.</p>
            <q>Many daughters have done vertuously, but Thou excellest them all, <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 31.29.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. Bedell,</hi> and <hi>T. Collins,</hi> at the Middle-Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Gate in Fleet-street; 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119344:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119344:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL and much honoured, Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Peyton</hi> Baronet, the dear Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of the ever memorable <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia</hi> Lady <hi>Peyton;</hi> Grace and Peace, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT neare Relation which you had by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugall tye to this most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Person: and that exceeding great kindness which shee had for you in that respect; as also upon the account of your owne worth: and that service (by me never to be forgotten) which I owe to her sacred memory, prompted me to some
<pb facs="tcp:119344:3"/>selves, but by setting the world a better pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne. In the meane time, may the love and faithfulnesse of such a Wife, and her Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary goodness towards others, but especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly her piety towards GOD, make such deep impressions in your selfe, as that you may really endeavour again to see and enjoy her in that place of blisse, where they neither mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor are given in marriage, but are like the Angels of God in heaven. Which shall alwayes be the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
               <signed>Your most humble and faithfully obliged Servant in the things of God, G. EVES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119344:3"/>
            <head>The Churches Patience, AND Faith in Afflictions.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MICAH 7.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>I will bear the indignation of the Lord, because I have sinned against him, untill he plead my cause, and execute judgement for me; he will bring me forth to the light, and I shall behold his righteousness.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words of dying persons, especially if they be wise and good, have alwayes beene esteemed of that force &amp; efficacy, that they have somtimes been look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as sacred; and have often amounted to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of a Law to those to whom they have been delivered. My Father, or my Mother, or my loving Husband, or such a deare friend gave me this in charge upon their Death-bed, and therefore I will not violate it upon any
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119344:4"/>termes: this is usuall language among ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and affectionate natures. And such I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume the greatest part of this Assembly to be, being the surviving friends and Relations of this Wise and Vertuous Lady, whose love hath constrained you to this uneasie taske of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting her body to the dust, that <hi>the eye which hath seene her may see her no more.</hi> Now then hearken ye to these memorable words w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> she recommended to you all upon her death-bed, and desired they might be imprinted in your hearts by this Exercise. That by the Churches example in generall, and her own example in particular, you might learne patiently to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the hand of God in all your troubles, and wait upon him, and believe in his mercy, that in due time he will deliver you and comfort you, as to her aboundant satisfaction he had done her. The impressions which this Text had wrought upon her owne soule, made her desirous it should be the subject of your Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations at her Funerall.</p>
            <p>In the words, there are contain'd these two Generall Parts. (1) The Churches Patience under Gods Chastisements. <hi>I will beare the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of the Lord, because I have sinned, &amp;c.</hi> (2) The Churches faith in Gods deliverance. <hi>Ʋntill he plead my cause, and execute judgement for me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the Churches patience there are two things considerable.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119344:4"/>
               <item>(1.) Her meek endurance of her afflictions, <hi>I will beare the indignation.</hi> I will not winch and stover at it, and strive by all meanes possible to throw off my burthen: But <hi>I will beare it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>(2.) There are the grounds of this her Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and they are two.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The first relates to God, because it was Gods hand that laid this load upon her, it was <hi>His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation,</hi> and therefore she would beare it, I will bear the indignation <hi>of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The second relates to her own sinne. Her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction was but the due desert of her transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: She was conscious to her self that she had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffended, and therefore she thus quietly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth her back to the correction. I will beare the indignation of the Lord, <hi>because I have sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Churches faith there are three things observable.</p>
            <p>First, she did believe that God would take her part against her Oppressors, and that two wayes. The one by asserting her innocency: That though she were faulty as to him, yet she had not deserved that they should deal so bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barously with her as they did: and therefore she believes that God <hi>will plead her cause.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other by executing vengeance upon her enemies, and repaying them their mischiefs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own bosoms. Untill he plead my cause <hi>and execute judgement for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, she did believe that God would
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119344:5"/>remove her burthen from off her shoulders. That he would turn her sorrow into joy, and make her darknesse to be light. <hi>He will bring me forth to the light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, she did believe that God would enlighten her mind, that she might understand the equity of his proceedings, and owne the truth of his promises; That he is a just and a righteous Judge punishing the wicked, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding his Saints. <hi>I shall behold his righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These are the several parts of the Text; and they are many, and my time but short: and I shall adde something also in the close by way of application, in reference to this present sad occasion. And therefore I must crave your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, if I rather hint at things then fully handle any thing.</p>
            <p>But before I enter upon the particulars, it will be requisite that I note to you, that the words of the Text will admit of a two-fold sense.</p>
            <p>The one literall, as referring to the Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians or other enemies of the Church, oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing and afflicting her. The other mysticall, as referring to the corruption of sinne, and to the malice and subtilty of the Devill, tyrannizing and infesting the mindes of men, and interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their peace▪ and breeding their great dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet. In both which sorts of affliction, the children of God do look beyond the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119344:5"/>and discover God correcting them, and therefore bear it patiently, as the <hi>issue of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation,</hi> &amp; so depend upon him for assistance and deliverance in both, whether outward or inward, temporall or spirituall. And therefore we shall indifferently make use of both senses, as occasion shall require.</p>
            <p>First then we shall begin with the patience of the Church, and her meek endurance of her afflictions. And here I shall note to you; That it is the duty and the practice of Gods people to bear the evils which he lays upon them with meekness and patience, in humility and silence to put their mouths in the dust, and not to murmure the least at Gods dealing with them: but <hi>aequo animo perferre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Junius in loc.</note> to beare and worke through them with an even and undisordered mind. It is the proper badge of a gracious child not to reply and turn again when his Father corrects him. So there is no better argument of the election of grace, and our adoption of sons, then our humble submission to the chastise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our heavenly father, of what kind so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be. There are indeed a sort of men who serve God upon that account that Satan falsely accused <hi>Job</hi> to serve him, <hi>(viz.)</hi> for the good wages which he usually payes them: But if he stretch forth his hand against them, and touch any thing that they have; if he shorten their blessings, if he blemish them in their ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, if he crosse them in their humours, if he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119344:6"/>pinch them in any thing wherein they most please themselves, then their leannesse makes them do that which <hi>Jeshurun</hi> did when she was waxen fat,<note place="margin">Deut. 32.15.</note>
               <hi>kicke against God.</hi> Presently they grow full of wrath, impatience and griese: and if they could tell which way possible to helpe themselves, they would never endure it. Now this is an argument of great weakness and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulancy of spirit, and serves no way to asswage, but tendeth rather to the encreasing of the evil. Away therefore with such mercenary hirelings, such Capernaitical disciples, that follow Christ more for the loaves than for the Gospell, and become of his family rather <hi>for the meate that perisheth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 6.27.</note>
               <hi>than for that meate which endureth unto everlasting life.</hi> But if provisions faile, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences arise, and they be like to suffer something for Christs sake, as censure of the world, losse or imprisonment, or it may be death it selfe, then farewell Christ; they like not to serve him at that rate. Certainly these men cannot possibly be of this society here in the Text. The true members of the Church of Christ equally accept of his stripts and his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces. For what they are, they are in him; and therefore they are content to <hi>follow him whither-soever he goes:</hi> they are willing to abide with him in every Condition, in poverty and plenty, in honour and disgrace, in sickness and health, in life and in death. His will is their law, his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure is their joy; and so they dispute nothing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119344:6"/>that he imposeth upon them. And if to try them and refine them, it be his good pleasure to cast them into the fornace, they <hi>glory in their tribulations;</hi> and take it as an argument of their proficiency in the doctrine of Christ, that he is pleased to put them to so hard a Lesson. And they do not grow sullen and dogged, and sit pouting and lowring, and refuse to learn it; but they conne it over with patience and humility, till they have got it perfect; and can willingly bear the indignation of the Lord.</p>
            <p>In the next place consider we the Grounds of the Churches patience: the first whereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to God, it was his hand, it was the <hi>Lords indignation,</hi> and therefore she would beare it.</p>
            <p>And truly this is a convincing argument to stop our mouths, and put a check to all our murmurings; That <hi>the Lord bath done it.</hi> He who made all things for himself, and therefore may mostreasonably dispose of every thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he sees good. Which of you wil not say with that housholder in the Gospel,<note place="margin">Mat. 20.15.</note>
               <hi>Is it not lawfull for me to do what I will with mine owne?</hi> And shall the great Creator, and the High Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessour both of Heaven and Earth, be abridged the liberty which his creatures think but equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to assume to themselves? If God should lay upon me all the miseries that my nature is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, yet my soule should justifie him that he can do me no wrong. This is that which struck <hi>David</hi> dumb,<note place="margin">Psal. 39.9.</note> when he was basely abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119344:7"/>by wicked men, and reproached by fools: he look'd beyond them, at the hand of God. And therefore as when <hi>Shimei</hi> railed upon him; <hi>Let him alone</hi> (sayes he) <hi>let him curse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.16.</note>
               <hi>for the Lord hath bidden him:</hi> So in that Psal. 39.9. <hi>I was dumb and opened not my mouth, because thou didst it.</hi> So that as it was else-where the aggravation of his griefe,<note place="margin">Psal. 55.12, 13, 14.</note> that his friends had afflicted him; <hi>It was not an enemie that reproached me, then I could have borne it; neither was it he that hated me that did magnifie himselfe against me, then I would have hid my selfe from him: But it was thon, a man mine equall, my guide and mine acquaintance. We tooke sweete counsell together, and walked unto the house of God in company.</hi> And therefore he lays a curse upon them in the next verse; <hi>Let death feise upon them, and let them go down quicke into hell,</hi> &amp;c Yet now here in this case, between God and his Church, a quite contrary course is to be taken; and we are rather to invert the words, and the manner of them thus. If it had been a man, mine equall, whether enemy or friend, I could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have born it: but it is Thou, my God, my Creator, my Redeemer, my continuall Preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, who hast given me my selfe, and all that I have; who when thou tookest away but a part, mightest have taken all; when thou tookest but a limb, mightest have taken away my life; and when thou mightest have taken away my soul, and cast it into eternal flames, thou tookest on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my temporall life, and that but to give me e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119344:7"/>in exchange: and therefore blessed, oh for ever blessed be thy holy name! <hi>I will thanke thee O Lord for giving me warning.</hi> Me thinks this consideration alone, that it is the Lords hand which filleth our cup; that it is he which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth us our measure, what we shall drinke, were enough to make us quietly to swallow down the bitterest potion; and to turne our madness into meekness, our perversnesse into patience, and all our pride and swelling into humility; and with all due submission and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience <hi>to beare the indignation of the Lord,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>His.</hi> And to say with good old <hi>Eli;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.18.</note>
               <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what seemeth him good.</hi> Yea, with Christ himself, when we see the cup may not pass away from us, but that we must drink it down: <hi>Oh holy father! not my will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.42.</note>
               <hi>but thine be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The second ground of the Churches Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence relates to her sin. She knew her selfe to be guilty of manifold transgressions, and therefore she resolves to bear her punishment patiently. I will bear the indignation of the Lord, <hi>because I have sinned against him.</hi> Yea, yea, that is the great make-bate between God and us; it is that which raiseth his indignation against us, and may justly keep us from replying, or venting one syllable of complaint, when his chastening is upon us. This is the argument wherewith the holy Ghost so convincingly stops the mouths of the murmuring Jews. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.39. <hi>Wherefore doth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119344:8"/>aliving man complain? a man for the punishment of his sins?</hi> There is a double force in the argument (1.) Wherefore doth a <hi>living man</hi> complain? One whom God hath spared in the thing that he most valueth <hi>(i. e.) his life. Skin for skin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 2.4.</note>
               <hi>and all that a man hath will he give for his life.</hi> (2) Where fore doth he complain when he is punished <hi>for his sin,</hi> whereby he hath forfeited his life? for <hi>the wages of sin is death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.2.</note> And therefore for <hi>a living man</hi> to complain, when God is punishing him <hi>for his sinne,</hi> is most unreasonable ingratitude. Indeed if I could meet with one who were a sufferer but no sinner, I could be contēted to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten a while, &amp; have the patience to hear what such a one could say for himself. But where is? where is he? <hi>There is not that man living that sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 8.46.</note> But to heare a sinner open his lips in this argument, a daily sinner, a grievous sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, who would not plead for God against him? and answer him as <hi>Michael</hi> did the Devill, when they were disputing about the body of <hi>Moses; I he Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude. 9.</note> Shall I that have a mass of original corruption, a vast lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of actuall trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions, desperate and wilful commissions of evill, ignorant and careless Omissions of good, vile actions, vain words, abominable thoughts lodging within me, and am not yet (it may be) willing to be cleansed from my filthiness, and part with my beloved darling lusts; shall I think any thing on this side death and hell hard mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure? Rather let my tongue cleave to the roof
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119344:8"/>of my mouth, then that I should murmur at the just proceedings of my God against me. No, <hi>I will bear the indignatiō of the Lord, because I have sinned against him.</hi> Well, but do you think this such a great matter? Truly in the judgment of St. <hi>Peter</hi> there is nothing glorious in it. <hi>What glory is it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. 2.10.</note>
               <hi>if when ye be buffeted for your faults, ye shall take it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently? But if when ye do well, &amp; suffer for it ye take it patiently, this is acceptable with God.</hi> Certainly if that only be acceptable with God, to take it patiently when we suffer for well doing; Oh! how unacceptable must it needs be, not to take it patiently when we are <hi>buffeted for our faults,</hi> not to bear the indignation of the Lord, when we have <hi>sinned against him?</hi> In a word therefore to conclude this point: Whatsoever crosse any amongst us lye under, whether it be loss in our Estate, or dishonor in our Reputatiō, miscaria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in our Children, unkindness of Friends, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciousness of Enemies, infirmities and diseases in our Bodies, trouble and disquiet of Minde, death of our nearest and dearly beloved Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or whatsoever other evill we groan under, let us pacifie our grief, and silence all our mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings, with this humble resolution of the Church here in the Text. <hi>I will bear the indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord, because I have sinned against him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come we now to the second genearll part of the Text; the Churches Faith. And here I told you she doth believe 3. things. The first where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, That God would take her part against her
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119344:9"/>Oppressors, and that two ways. (1) That God will assert her innocency, &amp;c. and plead her cause for her. <hi>Ʋntil he plead my cause.</hi> The truth is, though God be Judge of all the Earth, and will call his own children to an account for all their misdemcanours as well as others; yet still he hath that great tenderness for them, that he will not endure either men or Devils to be too busie and bold with them. But as he is their Judge, so he also becomes their Advocate, and pleads their cause for them. This is but the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of that promise, <hi>Ps.</hi> 109. <hi>v. ult. He shal stand at the right hand of the poore, to save him from those that condemn his soul.</hi> Although he himself have many things against them, (all which shall also in due time be taken up through his free grace and mercy in Christ;) yet as to men, <hi>he will bring forth their righteousness as the light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 37.6.</note>
               <hi>&amp; their judge ment as the noon-day.</hi> That the wicked World, and he who goeth for the God of it (I mean the Devil) shall be ashamed of those vile injuries and unjust reproaches, wherewith they have loaded them: and alter their opinion of them, as the Islanders of <hi>Melita</hi> did of <hi>Paul.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 28 3, 4, 5, 6.</note>
               <hi>When Paul had gathered a bundle of sticks, and laid them on the fire, there came a viper out of the heat and fastned on his hand. And when the Barbarians saw the venem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous beast hang on his hand, they said among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; No doubt this man is a murderer, whom though he hath escaped the sea; yet vengeance suffereth not to live. And he shook off the beast into the fire, and had
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119344:9"/>no harm. Howbeit they looked when he should have swollen, or fallen down dead suddenly: but after they had looked a great while, and saw no harme come to him, they changed their minds, and said that he was a God.</hi> Now this is usuall with God, thus to plead the cause, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to justifie the plea of those that trust in him,<note place="margin">Sept<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g.</note> &amp; depend upon him, and <hi>commit themselves to him that judgeth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously:</hi> So that though at the first, lewd fellows, sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> shall abuse them &amp; slander them, as they did their Mr. Christ before them, and accuse them for <hi>gluttonous &amp; wine-bibbers,</hi> for <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers and hypocrites,</hi> that they are <hi>beside them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, &amp; the Devil is in them,</hi> and such like stuff: yet at length they shall confess as the <hi>Centurion</hi> did of Christ hanging upon the Cross; <hi>Doubtless these men are the sons of God, and the servants of the most high.</hi> And therefore according to <hi>Gamaliels</hi> counsel, they shall <hi>refrain from those men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 5.38, 39</note>
               <hi>and let them alone, least haply they be found to fight against God.</hi> Thus God pleaded <hi>Davids</hi> cause against <hi>Saul:</hi> after all his envy, and in jury, &amp; ill words that he had wronged him with, see his last re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation and ingenuous acknowledgement in the last words that ever we read he spake to <hi>David. Then said Saul, I have sinned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.21</note>
               <hi>return my son David, for I will no more do thee harme, because my soul was precious in thine eyes this day: behold I have played the foole, and have erred exceedingly.</hi> And thus he pleaded <hi>Daniels</hi> cause with the Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Princes, <hi>My God hath sent his Angel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.22.</note>
               <hi>and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119344:10"/>hath shut tht Lions mouths, that they have not hurt me, forasmuch as before him innocency was found in me, and also before thee O King have I done no hurt.</hi> Yea thus did God plead <hi>Jobs</hi> cause with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil himself.<note place="margin">Job 2.3.</note>
               <hi>The Lord said unto Satan; hast thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered my servant Job, that there is none like him in all the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God, and escheweth evil? and still he holdeth fast his integrity, although thou movedst me to destroy him without cause.</hi> Yea, thus indeed he pleads the cause of all his against all the spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all assaults of Satan, and sinne, and sorrow, and doubting, and despair. See that Soul-reviving passage, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33, 34. <hi>Who shall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? it is God that justifieth. Who is he that condemneth? it is Christ that dyed, yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is risen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who also maketh intercession for us,</hi> &amp;c. And this is that which maketh true believers so wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to bear the indignation of the Lord; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they know, that in time convenient <hi>he will plead their cause.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other way wherein the Church belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth that God will take her part against her Adversaries, is by taking vengeance of them; That <hi>he will execute judgment for her.</hi> So the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee</hi> Paraphrast understands the words; <hi>Donec injuriam meam ulciseatur,</hi> untill he revenge my wrong. And truly this is usuall with God also, to plague those that hate his people, and cast them into the pit that they have digged for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119344:10"/>and bring about their mischievous inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon their own heads. Beside the frequēt Examples hereof in holy Scripture, the publick passages but of a sew dayes past will abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convince us, that it is dangerous medling with those that are Gods: for in due time he will revenge their quarrel, and <hi>execute judgment for them,</hi> though it may seem long first,<note place="margin">Hor.</note>
               <hi>Rarò an tecedentem scelestum descruit pede poena claudo.</hi> Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or never but vengeance overtakes the persecutors of the Church, though they be <hi>swif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the eagles of the heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 4.9.</note> as <hi>Jerusalem</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains hers were. And therefore though God be said sometimes to have leaden feet <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to follow heavily and slowly after them, yet in the end they shall finde him to have hands of steel, which wound deeply and deadly. Oh consider this <hi>as many as have evill will at Sion,</hi> and that deal untruly with the Israel of God.<note place="margin">Zech. 2.8.</note>
               <hi>Who so tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth them toucheth the apple of his eye. Who so trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth them shall bear his judgement whosoever he be.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay 10.</note> Neither will he less distress our spiritual adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, than he doth our temporal.<note place="margin">Rom 16.20.</note>
               <hi>He will bruise Satan under our feet shortly.</hi> Yea, our Lord Jesus Christ hath already <hi>spoiled principalities and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.15.</note>
               <hi>and made a shew of them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note>
               <hi>openly triumphing over them in his Cross, &amp; by his death destroyed him who had the power of death, that is the Devil.</hi> He is that <hi>Michael</hi> who fought with the great dragon, that old Serpent, called the Devil, and Satan, and prevailed over him, and <hi>cast him down out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc 12.7.10</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119344:11"/>
               <hi>from accusing his brethren before God day and night.</hi> Yea even we our selves also shal be <hi>mighty through him, to the pulling down of strong holds. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting downe imaginations and every high thing that exalteth it selfe against the knowledge of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4, 5.</note>
               <hi>and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Christ.</hi> And this is that which further encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth the Church to bear the indignation of the Lord, and to waite his leisure for redress, because she is assured that <hi>judgement shall be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted</hi> upon all her adversaries, she shall see her <hi>enemies covered with shame, and troden downe as the mire of the streets,</hi> as it sollows in the next verse.</p>
            <p>Well, but yet this is not enough to make the Church happy. For though it may be some sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to us, to see the Lord own our cause, and execute judgement for us, and make our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies suffer the evill which they intended to bring upon us: yet if we shall abide in darkness and the shadow of death; if we shall still like <hi>Ioseph</hi> continue in prison, untill our <hi>feet be hurt with fetters, and the iron enter into our soules,</hi> and obtain no release of our own miseries: Alasse it will be but a poor comfort to us <hi>Socios habuisse doloris,</hi> to have companions in our sufferings. Behold then in the next place, <hi>the Lord will send redemption to his people,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the second thing that the Church doth here believe; <hi>That God will bring her forth to the light.</hi> And this is true and solid comfort
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119344:11"/>indeed. When we are under a black cloud of afflictions, and the soul is benighted (as it were) with darkness, and dimness, and anguish of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; then to have the comfortable light of Gods countenance break forth upon us, it is no leste then life from the dead. Lo, this is the assurance of the Church here. There is nothing more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently promised and performed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oughout the whole Scripture. <hi>His anger endureth but a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; in his favour is life:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 30 5.</note>
               <hi>Weeping may endure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 97.10, 11.</note>
               <hi>The Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serveth the soules of his Saints: he delivereth them from the hand of the wicked. Light is sowne for the righteous, and gladness for the upright in he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt.</hi> That of the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> is also ful to this purpose. <hi>All that do wickedly shall be as stubble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Malac. 4.1, 2.</note>
               <hi>&amp; the day that cometh shall burn them up, saith the Lord of hosts, that it shall leave them neither root nor branch. But unto you that feare my name, shall the Sun of Righteousness arise with healing in his wings.</hi> Let me add but one Text more out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Esay In a little wrath I hid my face from thee for a moment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay 54.8.</note>
               <hi>but with everlasting loving kindnesse will I have mercy upon thee saith the Lord thy Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> Proofs to this purpose might be abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly multiplied. What should I instance in the Jews deliverance from that dismall destruction whereto wicked <hi>Haman</hi> had designed them?<note place="margin">Esther 8.</note> What should I instance in <hi>Iosephs</hi> unexpected freedom out of prison?<note place="margin">Gen. 41. Jer. 30.</note> Or in <hi>Ieremiah</hi> his edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction out of the dungeon, as out of the bowels
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119344:12"/>of hell into the light of life again? The time will not permit me to insist upon these things, as the nature and concernment of this truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. Let this then suffice; that there is no soul alive that truly trusteth in God, and waiteth for his salvation, but some time or other they have had some experimental feeling of this com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ort. How graciously God hath scattered and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the storms of their afflictions, the clouds of their sins, the mists of their ignorance, the damp of their manifold fears &amp; doubtings, the streams of griefe and lamentation that have run plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully down their cheeks; God hath removed them all, and turned their darkness into light. And therefore they can with a holy confidence take up that of the Apostle St. <hi>Paul: We had the sentence of death in our selves that we should not trust in our selves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.9, 10.</note>
               <hi>but in God which raiseth the dead. Who delivered us from so great a death, and doth deliver, in whom we trust that he will yet deliver us.</hi> Yea, though he bring thē down to the dust of death, and translate them into the land of darknesse where all things are forgotten: yet they know that they shall not always be forgotten, nor lye hid in the chambers of death for ever: but that there shall a day of glorious and eternall light dawn upon them, wherein they shall see him whom their soul loveth; and dwell with him in that inaccessible light, which all the powers of darkness shall not be able to obscure.</p>
            <p>There is but one thing more; and that is, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119344:12"/>Church doth here further believe, that God will enlighten her mind to understand the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of his proceedings, and the <hi>righteousnesse</hi> of his judgements, &amp;c. Indeed the dealings of God with men in this life, are many times very obscure, and hard to be understood. <hi>Thy way is in the darke, and thy footsteps are not known.</hi> The Apostle St. <hi>Paul</hi> breaks out into much admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them. <hi>Oh the depth of the riches both of the wisdome &amp; knowledge of God!</hi>
               <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m 11.33.</note>
               <hi>how unsearchable are his judgements, and his wayes past finding out!</hi> The Prophet <hi>David</hi> for his part did not know what to make of them: no more did the Prophet <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> for his, to see the wicked prosper, and the righteous oppressed. <hi>I thought to understand this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 11.33.</note>
               <hi>but it was too hard for me,</hi> says the one. <hi>Righteous art thou ô Lord when I plead with thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 1.1.</note>
               <hi>yet let me talk with thee of thy judgements: wherefore doth the way of the wicked prosper? wherefore are all they happy that deale treacherously?</hi> sayes the other. Indeed the <hi>righteousness of God is like the great mountaines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 36 7.</note>
               <hi>and his judgements are as a great deep,</hi> as the Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist speaks. The one too high for the low ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities of men, to be reached and measured by them: the other too deep for silly shallow flesh and blood to fathom the bottome thereof. And therefore till we plough with Gods heifer, there is no finding out his riddles; till he open our wits, there is no beholding and discerning his righteousness. What reason can there be given in nature, why sometimes wicked men, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119344:13"/>sometimes weak men should bear rule, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise dominion over multitudes both better and wiser then themselves? Who can tell, why some very hopefull persons should dye young; and others vile and useless in their generation should live and be old; and a third sort, both g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od and bad in differently, should be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the midst of their age? Onely the glasse of Gods word &amp; his will revealed, is that which gives us to see and understand his righteousness in a world of such like things as these are. Nay, in many things we are so dim-sighted, that even with a glass to help us, <hi>we see but darkely, &amp; know but in part;</hi> and in the midst of all our deepest disquifitions are at a stand, and know not which way to goe, either backward or forward. But when the day of the revelation of the righteous judgement of God shall appear, which the S<seg rend="sup">ts</seg> be lieve and look for: then all these knots shall be untyed, and all these riddles shall be unfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and explained. And we shall <hi>with open face behold the glory of the Lord,</hi> and see abundant cause to justifie those proceedings, which here we were too ready to censure and think hardly of. Yea we shall so see him, as thereby to become like him, and be transformed into his image, and be made partakers of his glory. And this is to behold his righteousness in a transcendent sense, so as to be made ours. And this is that which the Church especially believeth, and waiteth for: to see the finall manifestation of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119344:13"/>the righteousness of God, in the salvation of his Elect, and the condemnation of Reprobates. That as God is righteous in judging those who would not believe in him, nor obey the Gospel of his Son Christ Jesus: so he is righteous also, in saving those that did believe in his promises, and trust in his mercy, and lay hold of that sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction which Christ by his death had made for their sinne. <hi>He being made sin for them who in himselfe knew no sin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.21.</note>
               <hi>that they might be made the righteousness of God in him.</hi> And this is that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness which they do ultimately believe they shall behold, and enjoy the comfort of it to all eternity. And so I have dispatched the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness of the Text, as briefly as conveniently I could.</p>
            <p>And now that my work should seem to be in a manner over and done, I have my hardest task yet to peform. Namely, to give you a Funerall Relation of the life and death of this our deare deceased friend here before us. To whom next to my Mother that bare me, I do (under God) owe the greatest part of that little which I am, and have in the world. Of whom I confess there is much to be said: but I shall say but little in comparison, because I am afraid my passion will render me uncomely in the delivery of it: but I will prevent it what I can.</p>
            <p>First then, if I had time, I might shew you all along from point to point, how her health and her sickness, (with both which I have good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119344:14"/>to be well acquainted) were but a practicrl Comment upon this Text, which out of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of her heart she desired might be the Subject of this her Funerall Sermon. With what great humility, and invincible patience <hi>she bare the indignation of the Lord,</hi> both in the toubles of her health, &amp; in the puines of her so long and tedious sickness, taking all as from his hand; she hath here many witnesses. And that she thus bare it, upon the account of her having <hi>sinned against him;</hi> I am a secret witnesse of the many deep humiliations, and self-abhorrencies, and self-condemnations that I have severall times heard fall from her tongue, and the rivers of tears that I have seen run down her eyes. Desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring like <hi>Daniel</hi> in his confession,<note place="margin">Dan. 9.7.</note> to justifie God, and take to her self shame and confusion of face. And truly in that high degree: That shee told me, forasmuch as concerned her selfe, she did not care though the whole world were privy to all that ever she had done amiss, so little did she value the bubble of humane popularity. This was her patience, and this was her humility: thus <hi>to humble her selfe under the mighty hand of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.6.</note>
               <hi>that he might exalt her in due time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now for her Faith, it was no whit inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. As she wanted not enemies, some tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, but more spiritual; and with whom chiefly she contested: So <hi>she committed her selfe to God, to plead her cause, and execute judgement for her.</hi> And through his mercy, she lived to see him vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119344:14"/>her, and preserving her and hers, from those mischiefs which malicious men had been long contriving, and at last to see them catched in their own trap. But that wherein God espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially answered her faith, &amp; wherein she chiefly joyed, was her conquest over her Ghostly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Sin and Death, the Devil and Hell, over whom I heard her triumph (but a few days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her end) in those words of St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15 55, 56, 57.</note>
               <hi>O death where is thy sting! Oh grave! where is thy victory. The sting of death is sin; and the strength of sin is the law. But thanks be unto God, which giveth us the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory through our Lord Jesus Christ.</hi> And that she had overcome the world, take but this evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: She told us that while her dear Husband was in trouble, God was pleased to let her live, according to her desire and prayer, that she might be in some measure serviceable and assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant to him. But now that all was like to be setled in peace, and he was returned againe to a quiet enjoyment of his honour and estate, She thanked God that he was taking her away from the vanities of it. What could have been spoken more emphatically, to shew that <hi>the world was crucified unto her, and she unto the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal 6.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithstanding all this, it is not to be denyed, but that she had some clouds of feare and doubting, which did not a little darken her comfort for a while: and therefore she would be often complaining of the driness and barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119344:15"/>of her heart, and the coldness of her affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and of the weakness and want and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of her faith. Much lamenting that she could finde no more assurance of Gods favour, and of her own salvation and interest in Christ; a thing which she much harped upon all along her sickness. But God who is never wanting to those that seek him, and delight themselves in him, and hunger and thirst after his righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, at length gave her her hearts desire: and her own tongue confessed and uttered what her soule had so earnestly longed for: <hi>I am assured</hi> (faith she) <hi>I am assured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another time breathing out that pious eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation (as she did many others) <hi>Come Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, Come quickly:</hi> She immediately return'd her self answer; <hi>He is come, He is come.</hi> And at the same time praying to God to hear her and helpe her, she answered her self as before; <hi>It is done, It is done.</hi> Oh! what is the comfortable light of Gods loving kindness, and the blessed hope of salvation, and the unspeakable joy of believing if this be not? Take one testimony more of Gods discovering the light of his acceptance of her; as also of her zeal and humility in her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises of Devotion. Being to receive the holy Communion: (and that at a time of such great weakness, that the night before her Friends and Physitians thought her nigh unto death) she would needs take it upon her knees. And she hath since confessed, that how she got up upon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119344:15"/>her knees she knew not: but this she knew, that it was a very comfortable Communion to her</p>
            <p>I have yet another passage to acquaint you withal, worthy all your imitations. Of her own accord she told me; That she had lived in the faith of Christ, and did desire and resolve to die in it, and that if by reason of any weaknesse or distemper of sickness, or any suggestion of the Devill, she should either speake or thinke any thing contrary thereunto: She did desire me (twice) to take notice, that she did there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, utterly renounce &amp; disclaim it. Here was true Christian wisdom indeed, thus to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide and fortifie her self against a siege, in case her weakness might have been over-born: But Satan saw so little hopes, that he assaulted her not much, though somewhat he did. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now fought such a good fight, and thus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished her course, and so kept the Faith, what need we doubt, but that she now beholdeth the Righteousnesse of God, having received that <hi>Crown of Righteousness which the Lord the righteous Judge gave her</hi> (as he did St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>at the day of her departure.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But I have yet something more to add which falleth not within the compasse of the Text. Touching her Extraction, Birth and Parentage, I shall need to say nothing; being so well known by divers of you to be Ancient and Worthy. Onely this is not to be omitted; That she was the Daughter of a religious both Father &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119344:16"/>whose life she desired to imitate, &amp; whose death I have often heard her desire to dye. And truly I am perswaded, she came short of neither of them in either. And that she might have the better opportunity to attain the end, she had an especiall kindness for the Ministers of the Gospel, and delighted much to converse with them; and was several times at the charges of maintaining one in her own family: Of whom I shall ever account it my great happiness that I was one. And truly she told me (but this sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness) That if it pleased God to recover her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, she would never be without one as long as she lived; she had found the presence of a Minister to be such a Monitour and spur to the performance of good duties, and such a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint to sin and vanity.</p>
            <p>But though they had an especial place in her affection: yet generally she had a great respect for all good Christians of what ranke or degree soever, being full of civility to her Equals, and full of courtesie and bounty towards her Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and a hearty lover of all whom she did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be the Children of God. Which hath made me sometime upon occasion, (when she would be doubting of her salvation and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest in Christ) to use St. <hi>Johns</hi> argument to her; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat she was passed from death to life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 3.14.</note>
               <hi>because she lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the brethren.</hi> And indeed God had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly fitted her for an Exemplary instrument of doing good, having made her partner of a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119344:16"/>plentiful estate, and given her a willing miud; and compassionate affections, &amp; a very good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, to know where, and when, and what was to be done. Insomuch that to many sick people, especially those of the poorer sort, she was not onely a friend to visit and relieve them, but a Physitian and an Apothecary also, giving them counsell and physick both, and all gratis. The truth is, her Charity was a Grace, wherein she was superlatively eminent: Shee was eyes to the blind, feet to the lame, bread to the hungry, cloathing to the naked, a refuge and sanctuary to those that were harbourlesse. And as she was very charitable to her poore neighbors whom she knew, so she would often <hi>cast her bread upon the waters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 11.1.</note> not so much as loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after it which way it swom, because she knew that she should finde it again after many days. This hand of mine hath been a secret Messenger of many an alms which she hath sent to poor prisoners and persons in distress, whose faces she never saw. And truly sometimes it was in that abundant measure, that I have desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her to reserve some of it for another occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but the largeness of her heart would not permit her. So that though the sentence of sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation which Christ shall pronounce at the last day, can be due to none as of desert, yet I am perswaded it will be proper and suitable to her and her works, as to any she among ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand. <hi>Come ye blessed of my Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15.34, 35, 36.</note>
               <hi>inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119344:17"/>prepared for you from the foundation of the world. For I was hungry, and ye gave me meate: I was thirsty, and ye gave me drinke: I was a stranger, and ye tooke me in: Naked and ye cloathed me: I was sicke and ye visited me: I was in prison, and ye came unto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now she who was such a Foster-mother to the poor members of Christ in generall, must needs be a tender and affectionate Mother to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the issue of her own bowels, though her care and desire indeed was more for their spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall welfare then their temporall. It was a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to hear what pithy and pertinent admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions and Counsels she left to every one of them, agreeable to their severall conditions. The Lord give them all grace and wisdome to observe them. How also did she scatter her blessings among her friends about her! And when she could not by reason of weaknesse, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her selfe so freely as she desired; Oh (saith she) my heart is full of blessings for you all, more then my tongue is able to expresse. And to shew upon what peaceable &amp; friendly terms she was willing to take her leave of the World, and <hi>to agree with her adversary while she was yet in the way.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.25.</note> She said she was a woman, and had her failings, but she did heartily desire all people to forgive her what ever injuries she had done them in any kinde; and did freely forgive the whole world whatsoever wrongs they had done her. What then can be the reward of such
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119344:17"/>a peacefull soule, but peace eternall with the God of peace, in that world where strife and envy have no place?</p>
            <p>Oh what pity was it (to speak after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men) that she did not live to double those years of her pilgrimage here on earth! And yet if God had not graciously reserved her for the many good deeds which she hath since done, she had in all probability been taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by much such another sickness as this was, about 15. years ago: but God saw he had a <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah's</hi> spirit in hand, and therefore he then gave her a lease of her life for 15. yeares more: which is now expired, to the universall grief of all that knew her. I am verily perswaded, if all those who have any way tasted of her goodness, rich and poor, and those of the middle ranke, were all here assembled together at her funeral: It would be a <hi>very grievous mourning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 50.10.</note>
               <hi>a sore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation,</hi> like that of the <hi>Israelites</hi> for their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jacob,</hi> or that of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem</hi> for good King <hi>Josiah, like the mourning of Hadadrim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the valley of Megiddo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 12.11.</note> On the one side you might behold those eyes which she had cured, weeping themselves sore again. On the other side, you might heare those mouths which she had fed, and those bowels which she had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshed, yearning and lamenting that the staffe of their bread was broken. Behind, you might discover a long train as it were of <hi>Dorca's</hi> Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows following the Biere, those whose backs
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119344:18"/>she had cloathed, and covered their nakedness, rending their garments in excess of griefe; or with their sad tears, dying them into mourning for her. Indeed, who would seem so unconcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the good and comfort of so many poore Christians, as not to lament the losse of One so exceeding helpfull in her generation? If I should stand to relate all the severall passages which were worth the observing, in her life, and her death, in her health, and in her sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, I should hold you longer then St. <hi>Paul</hi> did the Disciples at <hi>Troas,</hi> even <hi>till past midnight.</hi> Let me therefore leave this short Character of her with you,<note place="margin">Acts 10.7.</note> in a few words: That (only aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting some grains of infirmity incident to our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature which must be allowed the best of men, and which love may easily cover) She was indeed and in truth, <hi>A most excellent, Noble-minded, Intelligent, Charitable, Highly-obliging, Religious Person.</hi> I delight to commend her. But I must put an end to this discourse; partly in obedience to her commands, who did indeed desire me not to do this for her: but I could not herein altogether hearken to her; partly out of compassion to my self, who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise could spend my spirits even to fainting in commending her: and partly in respect to you her friends, who, as you loved her, do now think it high time (as <hi>Abraham</hi> said of <hi>Sarah</hi>) <hi>to bury your dead out of your sight.</hi> What then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, but that we now addresse our selves to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119344:18"/>that last, but very uneasie office of committing her body to the grave? and therein as in a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet to lay her up as one of Gods jewels for a time, till he be pleased to bring her forth again in incomparable lustre and brightnesse, to help to adorn the Bride, at that great and solemne Matriage-Supper of the Lamb in the end of the World: when she and all others like her, who have lived in the feare of God,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.43.</note> and dyed in the faith of Christ, <hi>shall shine forth as the Sunne in the kingdome of their Father,</hi> and feast themselves with unspeakable joy and fulness, blessednesse and glory, for ever and ever. To which blessed and glorious estate He of his mercy bring us, &amp;c. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>